Finding aid to the Gena Corea papers SSC.MS.00242
Sophia Smith Collection
Gena Corea papers
1950-2011
Sophia Smith Collection
Corea, Gena
SSC.MS.00242
73.25 linear feet (61 boxes. Other materials in the collection: flat file.)
The Gena Corea collection documents the work of Corea, the director of FINRRAGE (Feminist International Network in Resistance to Reproductive and Genetic Engineering) and author writing on the politics of reproductive technologies in the international sphere.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is closed until Corea's death
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was recieved as a gift from Gena Corea between 1990 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Gena Corea is the author of"The Hidden Malpractice"(1977), concerned with how women were treated in the medical profession as patients and professionals;"The Invisible Epidemic"(1992), about the effect of AIDS on women;"Man-made Women"(1987) on reproductive technologies and their effect on women; and "The Mother Machine"(1985), about the medical and scientific establishment's increasing control of the reproductive process. Corea is director of FINRRAGE (Feminist International Network in Resistance to Reproductive and Genetic Engineering). She continues to research the politics of reproductive technologies in the international sphere and has traveled to Africa to study the AIDS epidemic there.
Scope and Contents
The Gena Corea Papers include records of FINNRAGE; published and unpublished writings; research and subject files; speeches; files pertaining to her column,"Frankly Feminist"; audiotaped interviews with AIDS victims and physicians; correspondence; photographs; and memorabilia.
Human reproduction--Social aspects--History--20th century; Women in medicine--United States--History--Sources; Women--Diseases--Research--Sources; AIDS (Disease)--Africa--Research--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene--Sociological aspects; AIDS (Disease) in women--Research--Sources; Women's rights--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Feminist International Network of Resistance to Reproductive and Genetic Engineering (FINRRAGE); Human reproductive technology--History--20th century; Women's health services--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Speeches; Manuscripts; Audiotapes; Research; photographs; memorabilia; correspondence; Interviews; Oral histories; diaries; Notes; articles; Computer media; Yearbooks; Corea, Gena; Corea, Gena
- Gena Corea projects "Stripping the Portuguese" and "The Zenaide Project", 1964-1999; 2001-S-0001; Corea, Gena; 10.5 linear feet (7 record cartons)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted by doner until Gena Corea's death
  General
  - Notes and drafts for "Stripping the Portuguese" play or book, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, notes and miscellaneous materials pertaining to Bangladesh, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with publishers, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and notes regarding women and gender, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 2)
  - Typescripts and photographs of Bangladesh, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials pertaining to women's issues, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 3)
  - Drawings and photographs, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 3)
  - Books on feminism and related women's issues by Gena Corea, Mary Daly and others, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, notes and typescripts, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 3)
  - High school and college yearbooks, 1964; 1968; 2001-S-0001 (Box 3)
  - Notes, clippings, miscellaneous materials related to population and birth control, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 4)
  - "Stripping the Portuguese" notes and typescripts, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 4)
  - Cassette tapes from Bangladesh trip, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 4)
  - Population and birth control books, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 5)
  - "Stripping the Portuguese" notes and typescripts, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 5)
  - Materials related to population and birth control, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 6)
  - Photographs of Bangledesh, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 6)
  - Notes and miscellaneous materials related to Barre, Vermont and stonecutting industry, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes and typescripts, undated; 2001-S-0001 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence to Ed and Marie Corea and others, 1968-1996; 2001-S-0001 (Box 7)
  - Books, pamplets, notes, typescripts, diaries related to in vitro fertilization and the "Zenaide Project", 1985-1989; 2001-S-0001 (Box 7)
- Gena Corea correspondence, research and published materials and photographs, 1969-2001; 2002-S-0024; Corea, Gena; 4 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Research files related to IVF project and The Mother Maxchine, undated; 2002-S-0024 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and articles, 1980-1989; 2002-S-0024 (Box 1)
  - Articles by other authors, undated; 2002-S-0024 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence, 1990-2001; 2002-S-0024 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1969-2000; 2002-S-0024 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous AV materials including computer discs and tape cassettes, undated; 2002-S-0024 (Box 2)
  - Research materials related to Northern Ireland, 1970-1979; 2002-S-0024 (Box 3)
  - Junior high and high school yearbooks, 1961; 1963; 2002-S-0024 (Box 4)
  - Personal correspondence, dream notes and pohotoigraphs, 1990-2001; 2002-S-0024 (Box 4)
- Gena Corea personal and professional materials including diaries, dream notes, memorabilia, notes for writing, 1970-2006; 2006-S-0079; Corea, Gena; 2 linear feet (3 boxes. Additional materials in flat files.)
  Restrictions designated by the donor: The restrictions applied to the accession record are the same as those applied at the collection-level.
  - Biographical information and family history, 2006; undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 2006; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Notes and emails related to dreams, 1999; undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Baystate Correctional Center notes and fliers, 2003; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Notes related to classes and workshops, 1996-2005; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2006; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and artwork, undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - "These Words" audiocassette, 2001 September 11; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology Alumni Register, 1975; 2006-S-0079 (Box 1)
  - Date books and diaries, 1995-2006; 2001-2006; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - materials related to U.S. presdential campaign, 2004; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - U.S. government publication on drug industry, 1970; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writing notes and drafts, 2004; undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2005; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1970-1979; 2004; undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Bangladesh and miscellaneous, 1990-1999; undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, poster and artwork, undated; 2006-S-0079 (Box 4)
- Gena Corea materials related to proposed documentary, miscellaneous photographs and book about parents, 1968-2007; 2008-S-0023; Corea, Gena; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - transcripts and notes for proposed documentary, 2006-2007; undated; 2008-S-0023 (Box 1)
  - "The Marie and Ed Book", 1981; 2008-S-0023 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1968-1993; undated; 2008-S-0023
- Gena Corea miscellaneous personal and professional materials, 1980-2011; 2011-S-0034; Corea, Gena; 1 linear feet (1 box)
  - Journal and calendars, 2001-2008; 2011-S-0034 (Box 1)
  - Financial records, 1980-1999; 2011-S-0034 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993-2011; 2011-S-0034 (Box 1)
  - Research files and drafts for books, undated; 2011-S-0034 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of 60th birthday party, undated; 2011-S-0034 (Box 1)
- Gena Corea personal correspondence, unpublished writings, notes, photographs, memorabilia, 1950-1999; 1980-1999; 1999-S-0044; Corea, Gena; 2.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Personal correspondence, photographs and memorabilia, 1950-1999; 1999-S-0014 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, drafts and other materials related to writings, 1950-1999; 1999-S-0044 (Box 1)
  - Family tree and correspondence, 1980-1999; 1999-S-0044 (Box 2)
  - "Stripping the Portuguese" drafts, 1980-1999; 1999-S-0044 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous personal and professional notes, 1980-1999; 1999-S-0044 (Box 2)